Finding Aid for Mount Zion African Methodist Episcopal Church records, 1925-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mount Zion African Methodist Episcopal Church records 1925-2008
Mount Zion African Methodist Episcopal Church (Battle Creek, Mich.)
4 linear feet
2008130 Aa 2
Battle Creek, Michigan African American church; conference records, minutes and agendas from church meetings, financial documents, member lists, various church bulletins, and collected historical documents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were first deposited by Frank R Brown (donor no. 10077 ) in 2008. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Mount Zion African Methodist Episcopal church traces its history back to around 1855, when Elder James Brown and his wife established a church in Battle Creek. Initially, the congregation met in members' homes, but by 1867 the church had taken up residence at its current location on Van Buren Street. The current church was built between 1906 and 1908, and adopted the name, Mount Zion AME, in 1926. In 1991, the church was listed on the State Register of Historical Places. The church expanded its building in 2004.
The Mount Zion AME church records date from around 1925 to the present, and document various aspects of the church, its members, and the surrounding religious community. The record group has been arranged into two series: Church Administrative Records and Church Activities and Membership.
Subjects:
African American churches--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Church history.; Mount Zion African Methodist Episcopal Church (Battle Creek, Mich.)
Contributors:
Brown, Frank R.
- Church Administrative Records 1931-2007
  The first series, Church Administrative Records, consists of records from various internal and local conferences, agendas and minutes from the church's administrative boards, and financial documentation.
  - Steward Board Meeting Minutes 1979-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Steward Board Meeting Minutes 1994-2003 (Box 1)
  - Steward Board, Finance Reports1979-1994 (Box 1)
  - Trustee Board Minutes 1931-1937 (Box 1)
  - Trustee Board Minutes 1987-1997, undated (Box 1)
  - Trustee Board Minutes 1998-2003 (Box 1)
  - Church Conferences 1985-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - District Conferences 1998-2006 (Box 1)
  - Quarterly Conference Journal 1943-1952 (Box 1)
  - Quarterly Conferences 1974-1990 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Quarterly Conferences 1985-2007 (Box 1)
  - Conference Bulletins 1954-2003 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Official Board Agendas and Meetings 1992-2000 (Box 1)
  - Official Board Budgets and Calendars 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Official Board and Church Conferences 1986-1996 (Box 1)
  - Official Board Minutes 1979-2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Financial Ledger 1931-1936 (Box 2)
  - Mount Zion Rental Property 1974-1980 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (includes certificates, legal documents, and materials of casual interest)
- Church Activities and Membership 1925-2008
  The second series, Church Activities and Membership, is arranged into four subseries. Membership includes new and active member lists from 1925 to 2008, records of baptisms, and obituaries and memorial resolutions. Bulletins and Church Publications includes copies of church bulletins from 1970 to 2007, along with assorted programs and newsletters for events and special services, and Sunday School minutes. Building Expansion, Historic Site Designation, and Church Anniversaries documents the growth of the church building, its designation as an historic site by the State of Michigan and the city of Battle Creek, and celebrations of the church's anniversaries. Histories of the Church and Church Activities includes histories of the church, its choirs and musical programs, pastors, and the Women's Missionary Committee, compiled by the church's historian, Frank R. Brown, and the church's Black Heritage Committee. The majority of the histories contain historical narratives, photographs of church members, events, and facilities, photocopies of documents, and clippings.
  - Membership
    - Official Membership 1944-2006 (Box 2)
    - Membership Directory 2008 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists 1925-2006 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Record Book with Membership Roll circa 1933-1939 (Box 2)
    - New Member Lists 1944-1948, 1989-1998 (Box 2)
    - Inactive Members 1994, undated (Box 2)
    - Baptism Certificates (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Church Members Meetings 1993 (Box 2)
    - Class Leaders Minutes and Lists 1980-2003 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Memorial Resolutions (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Obituaries 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins and Church Publications
    - Memorial Service Bulletins 1980-2006 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Sunday Bulletins 1970-1989 (Box 2)
    - Sunday Bulletins 1990-1999 (Box 3)
    - Sunday Bulletins 2001-2007 (Box 3)
    - Assorted Bulletins 1948-2007 (Box 3)
    - Sunday School Minutes 1952-1972 (Box 3)
    - Church Newsletters 2005 (Box 3)
    - State Rally Banquet Programs 1994, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Black Heritage Programs 1993-2001 (Box 3)
  - Building Expansion, Historic Site Designation, and Church Anniversaries
    - City of Battle Creek--Historic Preservation Proclamation 1993 (Box 3)
    - Building Expansion Project 2002-2004, 4 folders (Box 3)
      (includes photographs of members active in the expansion project)
    - Mt. Zion AME Church Historic Site, 1855-1995 (Box 3)
    - 140th, 145th, 150th Anniversary Materials 1995-2005 (Box 3)
  - Histories of the Church and Church Activities
    - Camp Baber, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Mt. Zion AME Church 80th Musical Anniversary, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Mt. Zion AME Church Choirs, 1855-2005 (Box 4)
    - Mt. Zion AME Church Legal Documents, 1855-1995 (Box 4)
    - Mt. Zion AME Church Pastors, 1855-1995 (Box 4)
    - Reflections (A Pictorial History of Mt. Zion AME Church), 1850-1990 (Box 4)
      (Includes newspaper clippings and photographs of congregations and individual church members)
    - A Story in Pictures, 1906-2003 (Box 4)
      (Includes photographs of church members, buildings, and pastors)
    - Today's Young Minds Our Investment in the Future (Annual Black History Program), 1996 (Box 4)
      (Includes photographs, civil rights timeline, and Mt. Zion AME church history)
    - Women's Missionary Society (A Photograph Album and Brief History), 1995 (Box 4)
      (Includes discussion of Women's Missionary Society, photographs of past presidents of the society, and photographs of groups and individual members)
    - The Vision Made Real (The History of Mt. Zion AME Church), 1855-2000 and 1855-2005, 2 volumes (Box 4)
      (Includes church history, notes about important church figures, and discussion of Mt. Zion as a historical site)